[SPEAKER_01]: So, I thought we could speak about celibacy, sexuality, since it's quite an important point for most people who are practicing most monastics.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'll be reading from the Anguttara Nikaya, the numerical discourses of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha, he said in the beginning, the Book of the Ones, actually, because I do not see even one other form that so obsesses the mind of a man as the form of a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: The form of a woman obsesses the mind of a man, and likewise, vice versa with the... for a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the form of a woman, the smell, the whole experience of a woman, obsesses one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, every sense, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: The form, the smell, the touch, those...
[SPEAKER_01]: It says those who are bound by the sense of touch are thoroughly bound.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you can have the image of the... see the woman, but once she... when you have the touch, that experience binds you thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, OK.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the last drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the last thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he goes, on another sutta, goes on to say, because there are three things that give no satiation, or are insatiable, by indulging in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: What three?
[SPEAKER_01]: By indulging in sleep, by indulging in alcohol,
[SPEAKER_01]: By indulging in sexual intercourse, these are three things that give no satiation by indulging in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no ending to... To the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, more specifically, in regard to those three things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never have enough of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think most people would feel like they already know that, like desires are not... cannot be really satisfied and so on, but if you... obviously, if you really understand it, if you would genuinely understand it, that it's insatiable,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you will actually lose an interest in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is inherently, structurally, pointless, impossible to...
[SPEAKER_00]: The promise that it has of whatever, satisfaction, gain, pleasure, is just... it is hollow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it cannot be satisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, okay, so giving in once means you... then you... you'll be... it will be harder for you to not give in another time.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you give in another time, then it'll be even harder for you to not give in again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, you develop a habit of giving in to something that you know it's utterly pointless.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, like, even somebody who doesn't necessarily want... aims at arahantship as a goal, or anāgāmī, or whatever, he will be better off by being silhouetted, even as a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be much better for the mind, for general wisdom, for general wholesomeness of life, and obviously for rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, because you spend your mind, you spend your human life not engaging in kind of animal-like, I don't know, activities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're gonna have a better destination as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what is it for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like getting drunk?
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no fulfillment, no goal, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like knowing that scratching of the itch won't remove the itch, but you just enjoy the scratch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing that that scratch is actually making the itch even worse, so next time it's gonna make it even harder, even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you know that this is not even a temporary end to the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just oblivion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through itching, that's making things worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you depend on the itch even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you depend on the bleeding more, which means you're making things worse even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like the vicious circle and the downward spiral of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But some would say that it's only natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sexual intercourse is only natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nature is what saṃsara is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature keeps you bound to evil.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, it is very natural.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very natural to be evil.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very natural.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone once said, it's natural, but not necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sexual intercourse, there's no... Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is a saying, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, I don't know in what context they meant natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some of these people... Well, people, when they say it's natural nature, they think it's this kind of a whole, great, a good thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimately, it is the very nature, even the nature of things, and your ignorance in regard to it, that keeps you bound.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you're responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't blame the nature of things, but nature is set up as a trap, as a deceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you give in involuntarily, almost.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's normal to take things at face value.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's normal to entertain ignorance in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what nature is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people say natural, then it's bad faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not my fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's dismissing all the responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... it's not really up to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... just a... a natural need that needs a natural satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the result's a natural rebirth, a natural liberate, a natural saṃsara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's three things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sleep, drugs, alcohol, sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, they just, they love each other, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it just works so well together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: It hasn't helped.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's another sūtra I will read.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's from the Guṭṭarīka Nikaya as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's called Mother and Son.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's quite a intense sūtra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another.
[SPEAKER_01]: On one occasion, the Blessed One was dwelling in Savatthi, in Jesus' grove.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, on that occasion, a mother and son, being respectively a bhikkhuni and a bhikkhu, had entered the rains residence at Savatthi.
[SPEAKER_01]: They often wanted to see one another.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mother often wanted to see her son, and the son his mother.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they often saw one another, a bond was formed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because a bond formed, intimacy arose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there was intimacy, lust found an open.
[SPEAKER_01]: With their minds in the grip of lust, without having given up the training and declared their weakness, they engaged in sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, a number of bhikkhus approached the Blessed One, paid homage to Him, sat down to one side and reported what had happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Blessed One said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I do not see even one other form that is as tantalizing, sensuous, intoxicating, captivating, infatuating, and as much of an obstacle to achieving the unsurpassed security from bondage as the form of a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beings who are lustful for the form of a woman, ravenous, tied to it, infatuated, and blindly absorbed in it, sorrow for a long time under the control of a woman's form, with the experience of a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of their sound, their smell, their taste, their touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because while walking, a woman obsesses the mind of a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: While standing, while sitting, while laying down, while laughing, while speaking, while singing, while crying, a woman obsesses the mind of a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: When swollen, too, a woman obsesses the mind of a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when dead, a woman obsesses the mind of a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: If because one could rightly say of anything, entirely, snare of Mara, it is precisely of a woman that one could say this.
[SPEAKER_01]: One might talk with a murderous foe.
[SPEAKER_01]: One might talk with an evil spirit.
[SPEAKER_01]: One might even approach a woman whose bite means certain death.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with a woman, one-to-one, one should never talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: They bind one whose mind is muddled with a glance and a smile, with their dress in disarray, and with their gentle speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is not safe to approach such a person, though she is swollen and dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: These five objects of central pleasure are seen in a woman's body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Forms, sounds, tastes, and odors, and also the delightful touches,
[SPEAKER_01]: Those swept up by the flood of sensuality, who do not fully understand sense pleasures, are plunged headlong into saṃsāra, into time, destination and existence upon existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those who have fully understood sense pleasures, live without fear from any quarter, having attained the destruction of the taints, while in the world they have gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just to be said,
[SPEAKER_00]: It works the same the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: For a woman, it's the form of a man.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sex, you can just replace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, I don't even want to have to address it, but I think some people might...
[SPEAKER_00]: When they read things like that, obviously, they read it with no wisdom or not even enough transparency to see what it refers to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they take it personally and think the Buddha was blaming women or the Buddha was blaming men.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the nature of things is that you, with the mind affected with ignorance, will be snared by a form of a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: A woman's mind, affected with ignorance, will be snared by a form of a man.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't actually mean that that particular woman or that particular man are responsible for that snare.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just carry this form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, they're responsible for their own ignorance in regard to their own form that was given to them circumstantially.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not on the level of a full-on clear volition, that every woman is out to get every man, or that every man is out to seduce every woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply by taking a masculine form, by assuming it, that's basically that masculine aspect of it, which you yourself had nothing to do with.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, a man is a victim of his own masculinity, as much as a woman is, that is being affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another way around, a woman is also a victim of her own femininity, as much as the man is snared by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another sutra where the Buddha says, by giving in,
[SPEAKER_00]: To the notions of your own masculinity, you make yourself liable to be, basically, to be snared by the opposite, by the female, by the feminine notions and feminine forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same for a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: By entertaining, by delighting in her femininity, she maintains herself liable to a snare of her male form, of the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one's own doing, one's own delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The lust is found in your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that, you can say that, like in this particular sutta, that female form that snares a man, it's the same female form that traps a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can say that the male form that snares a woman, the masculinity that snares a woman, it's the same masculinity that traps a man.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, again, in another sutra, it was said you should look at your own body, at your own... not the light in your masculinity as a man or femininity as a woman, and look at it as we discussed that you would look on a pile of feces on the road.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would avoid it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't step in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you actually, in order to not be snared by a form of a woman, a man needs to actually abandon the light and holding on to his masculinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean he needs to become feminine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means he needs to not regard the given masculinity as belonging to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was given to no one.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has just arisen and it will cease when the aggregates break apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no need for him to take it up and interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This thing goes for a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: Her femininity is a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was given.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Determined by chance, by elements, by previous lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just how it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she's fully responsible for taking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she'll be fully responsible for freeing herself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If she doesn't take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean she has a sex change and becomes a man or something like.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just simply means whatever has a reason, you leave it as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then that femininity for a woman will not attract her.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by not being attracted into that, that is liable, basically, to be snared by the opposite, by the masculinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: She won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: She won't be snared by neither.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're responsible.
[SPEAKER_00]: A man is responsible for dwelling, for entertaining, for delighting, for holding on to,
[SPEAKER_00]: His masculinity, because of that, he's liable to snap.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sort of comes and covers up that field of masculinity where he abides carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he were to withdraw his mind from that notions of masculinity, he can be very masculine externally, but his mind is not taking it to be his.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, he doesn't need to go through, like a, I don't know, a retraining of his, like, speech or behavior and become refined, soft-spoken and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just management of external circumstances, which were never a problem in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means that management is completely misguided.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever's, like, you know, if your habits are coarse, whatever...
[SPEAKER_00]: If your habits are coarse, or whatever, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is, you don't actually appropriate the pictures at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: For a man, that picture is masculine to man.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he can stay masculine, as long as that masculinity doesn't belong to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same for a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: She can... Obviously, that will limit the amount of your interaction, so to speak, or the amount of actions you will do on account of that masculinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, somebody who is entertaining that masculinity will obviously be revolving on.
[SPEAKER_00]: A woman who delights in her femininity will obviously be putting that forward, her feminine side.
[SPEAKER_00]: She'll be indulging it, taking it a step further, developing it, refining it, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that won't be done by the person who has abandoned either masculinity or femininity, respectively.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that they have to undo whatever has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're a man.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were born in a male gender.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were born in a female gender.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, because whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know the escape from it, which is usually when people try to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's genderless, it's beyond gender.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gender is given.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your body is your world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It determines it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It determines the intentionality behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It determines all desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't have to take it to belong to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's what Arunagiri is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So a woman can stay a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: She'll stay a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she can be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, she won't be doing anything on account of sensuality, or anything on account of appropriation of the body, which she has completely freed herself from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, her mind goes beyond it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean that you deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: She still knows the fact that this is a female body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same for a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... what about the...
[SPEAKER_01]: He could... well, he could make the other... by entertaining his masculinity, he knows what he's doing as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's attracting that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it can be... it can be done intentionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no doubt about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's seduction.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter who does it to who.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, that would be impossible if a man... like, a man wouldn't be able to seduce a woman if he's not giving notions and appropriating and delighting in his masculinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same.
[SPEAKER_00]: A woman who has given up her femininity wouldn't be out trying to seduce men.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor would she be out... or even delighting in the notions of being liked by men or being disliked by men.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't matter to her.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't matter to a man.
[SPEAKER_00]: If every, if every... Look, look, look, I am venerable ānurūḍa, the arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was, apparently, in the suttas, he was still very handsome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, lots of women, just, you know, Venetian women were not familiar with Buddhism, were trying to try to seduce him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, a number of our rules revolved around that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, not to belong... because the stories didn't get happened to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, he was all avoiding it, always he was an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the Buddha said, well, somebody who's not an arahant
[SPEAKER_00]: They might quite likely give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, all the rules have evolved around being secluded with a woman and so on, to be avoided.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was... it was around the stories when... when he, you know... and there are quite a few... few times his name would come up, because he was clearly still attractive to the... to fit... to... to women.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he was not earned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he wasn't entertaining it, nor was he out trying to seduce it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, obviously, the other minds, they were still kind of trapped by their own femininity, would find this form that comes in their range, a form of vendra-bhāna-mṛda, attractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, she's trying...
[SPEAKER_01]: Inkeeper, the woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When she go to me now, I'll... don't stay in this crowded.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll give you a security.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll give you a special room.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, then she go into special room.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then she... when... when he did not respond to her advances, then she... she felt, oh, kind of a bit ashamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, actually, impressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because she said... Obviously, she was also good-looking according to her own account, because she said, many people try to, you know, pay her wealth just to spend the night with her, and loads of...
[SPEAKER_00]: But here, look, I'm offering myself to this, this, this reckless, and he's not even looking at me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then she dressed herself, apologized, and took a refuge within dhamma, because she was so inspired by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's a sutta about Dānaputra, the actor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he asked the Buddha, where will I be reborn as an actor?
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says, don't ask me that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the actor comedian.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, comedian.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So don't ask.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask the Buddha three times.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to know this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said,
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, other actors say that because he's an actor, a comedian, he makes people happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, in the realm of the laughing devas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said to her, I'm afraid not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're being born in the laughing hell, in the realm of the laughing hell.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he started crying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he was so actually happy, that now he found the right way, that he shouldn't be... Yeah, the Buddha thought he was crying, and he said, see, I told you don't ask me, because I knew, like, you know, your world would be shattered.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, no, no, no, I'm not crying because I'm upset.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm crying because I'm not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I've been told the truth, finally, and, like, I've been lied all this time, that by being a comedian, I'm going to be reborn in this comedic heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... but now I've shown you the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you went forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as the Buddha said, you encourage others in greed, hatred, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, basically, the minds of others, when they're not free from greed, aversion, delusion, they come towards you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you, with your mind, which is not free from greed, aversion, delusion, perform actions that make them laugh, and make their greed, aversion, delusion, increase.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, like, basically, audience is full of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actor is full of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the whole result of it is more increasing greed, aversion, delusion, like euphoria or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just making things much worse than they actually are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people's happiness revolves around sensuality, most often.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even comedy or whatever, just making happy, laughing, basically through distraction, through carelessness and so on, we just bring all the asuras that are already there to increase.
[SPEAKER_00]: The taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the taints, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's the worst thing with that innkeeper woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mukeshwar, she went... she changed her ways, but... encouraging lust in others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that is your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the... yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you're developing your masculinity in order to seduce, to infect minds of others with more lust and aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that... in that way, you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, that is, you know, because that is intentional action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody setting on to seduce a woman or a woman to seduce a man, and then that results in their mind being infected by lust, aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all basically... Well, there is a good deal of shared responsibility in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, they're responsible for being ignorant in the first place, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: For being in the domain of lust, for keeping themselves in the domain of lust, for giving in to lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can always say no.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, the seducer has his own take.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take of that type of...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think of, like, this actor, now you think pornography.
[SPEAKER_01]: Purpose of it is entertainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purpose of it is basically fiction, taking the mind away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Romance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, you know, it's done selectively.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you do a romantic movie.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you show the romantic things, romantic build-up, drama, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't actually show everything in a human life, because people probably grossed by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting up, you know, having diarrhea, and then going meeting your loved one for coffee, and still having to run to the toilet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you show that in a movie, it will not be a romantic movie.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you only show the poignant bits.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not what life is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've heard it before, you've heard it as well, that to overcome
[SPEAKER_01]: That is beyond stupid, that I will not even talk about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me something I'll mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I think, some people think that to entertain those sexual energies is... Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people do, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for example, the whole tantric practice, in inverted commas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, people try to overcome it, one way or the other, and they can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have absolutely no idea how to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what do they do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, they make a practice out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then, they will feel like, no, no, no, this is the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will feel like they're overcoming it, overcoming the coarseness of sensuality, while still remaining very much engaged in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they just end up... the whole purpose of that whole thing is just to lie to yourself, to mask responsibility, to mask the failure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not able to say no to a desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not able to overcome the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, no, no, it's not about overcoming.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Engaging with it, teasing it, adding to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must not deny that energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only a person who cannot overcome it will say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because otherwise, he'll have to admit to himself they're weak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're not worried, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Worry of the goal they made themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Set forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without declaring their weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the Buddha's sentence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without declaring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it would be actually much better if they would be authentic enough, transparent enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: To admit that they're weak, no matter how bad it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that bad feeling will... might actually make them make proper effort further down the line.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they give in and cover it up and say, no, no, no, it's not about...
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not weakness.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Strength is giving up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not giving up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're not supposed to give up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're supposed to entertain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's only a weak person would say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: A person who doesn't know how to give it up, and the only choice for him is to entertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what he ends up doing is basically just, same as before, entertaining sensuality, just kind of developing a different excuse for it, or a more elaborate, or a more meaningful background.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I don't know, it's a spiritual practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, because it's just going to be very, very coarse.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're saying that the sense of shame disappears there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you would, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You become stronger than it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cover the sense of shame when you decide to cover the feeling of guilt for not being able to say no.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your sense of shame goes with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you covered it, you covered it up as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's taken to be progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're not embarrassed anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, there is that practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you don't feel a sense of shame, doing shameful things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, all this sense of shame, basically, it's not natural, it's the product of society, and you're really going to be empowered if you ignore that it's shameful, and then just go ahead and do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody should tell you how to live your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is what modern society kind of encourages, one way or the other, because, again, the sense of shame bothers you, the feeling of guilt bothers you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you blame others for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't recognize that there is a natural aspect to a sense of shame and feeling of guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, if the whole society is repressed, yeah, it's delusional, repressed, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, that doesn't mean you should deny the entire sense of shame on a personal level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is quite natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, these are the natural protectors of the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without a natural sense of shame, well, men would be like dogs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Brothers sleep with sisters, sisters with fathers, mothers with sons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, just, just, they would be complete, completely serene.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it bothers people.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't know how to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't have any wisdom in regard to it, to recognize it yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a
[SPEAKER_00]: There is an overflow of, like, shaming and guilt by the society, certain societies in some, I don't know, depressed countries or whatever else, but that doesn't mean that that... that that is the entire thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the personal aspect of that sense of shame, because, yeah, it's a shameful thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a private thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and people can't draw that line.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't see the line.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they rebel against it, they rebel against the whole thing, and they become utterly shameless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you feel liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another word people use.
[SPEAKER_00]: Liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because suddenly, you feel free.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like a liberation of... of just giving... opening the floodgates of the desire even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or there's... now there's nothing stopping you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before, you actually had that sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you mistook it to be something that it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You denied it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You made the effort to cover it, to destroy it, to ignore it, to rebel against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you feel liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a liberation of just outpour.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, sure, it feels a relief when you open the gates, but you wouldn't feel a relief if you were to know where these floods are taking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they're taking you down the messy waterfall, you're gonna crash at the bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will not feel a relief if somebody opens the gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will feel life-threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on the contrary, you would feel relieved if the gates could stay closed, so you don't flow down the waterfall where you're gonna crash into death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not knowing that, yeah, oh, yeah, it's a joyous ride until, oh, it's too late now to swing back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's one approach trying to escape such things, sensuality, is to take tantric, is tantric Buddhism, tantric, you know... Ah, it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contradictions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sexual celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tantric Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, Buddha, he goes on to encourage celibacy, brahmacharya, and there's a sutta on that, where he describes what that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some would say this is the other extreme, like complete suppression of all these desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's just not this restrictive.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're beating yourself up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You suppress the desires because you see them pointless, meaningless, insatiable, and only result in harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, by all means, suppress it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through that suppression, wisdom might arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: One thing for sure, wisdom will not arise from giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wisdom will not necessarily arise through somebody who is practicing full-on restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wisdom will not necessarily arise just from that, but it can.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one thing for sure, it cannot arise if there is no basis of restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another sutra where it says, even if somebody spends their whole life without, kind of, developing any wisdom, just through sheer restraint and saying no to desires, and even if they go through extreme pains because of that, and spend their whole life in tears for the rest of their life, it's still much better than giving in, like, just once.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in the long run, again, you spend years
[SPEAKER_00]: Forcefully, for somebody with no wisdom, keeping the mind away from giving into centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's making lots of merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, people think merit...
[SPEAKER_00]: For the future life, it's just through giving.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that was the lowest aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I said, yeah, through giving, through giving to one person, to Mopa, to the Buddha, to Arahant, to Saṅgha, you get more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But none of that would equal the amount of merit, the streams of merit you would make, like if you develop a finger snap of a right view, a finger snap of freedom from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: A finger snap of non-cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finger snap of loving-kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: A finger snap.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody for a whole lifetime... That's what I meant when I said in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if somebody doesn't want to be an arahant or whatever, it would be much better if they would practice celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they would say no to sexual desire, the mind would already grow by itself just through that, let alone if they make extra effort to gain wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's painful for the rest of your life, so what?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, what, measly 50-60 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: How many years have you been reborn?
[SPEAKER_00]: How many years you will be reborn on account of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: 50 years of crying your eyes out because of the pain of restraint?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will go up in smoke.
[SPEAKER_00]: No time.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pain of restraint or the fever of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that's like, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: The most, the many you can imagine, just practicing sensual restraint, non-cruelty towards people, non-entertaining yourself, not your desires, for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what about...
[SPEAKER_00]: Eons of heavenly rebirth, because those are the mental states, they will take you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But maybe I'm... if I have children, giving them opportunity to... to hear the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I don't follow that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, people have children they want to give.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've heard it before, that you want to give other beings... Ah, no, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they had children in order for those children to later have opportunity to get dharma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that sounds... sounds like a terrible excuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about... because there is no guarantee you're going to become an arahant, even if you hear the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, hearing the dhamma in itself can be quite meaningless, if a person doesn't know how to attend to it, or doesn't want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you can say to those people who want to have children, in order for children to hear the dhamma, maybe, it would be better if they become arahants themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Optional, a remote possibility of somebody becoming an arahant by hearing the dhamma in the future, they can become arahants themselves and learn one lesson saṃsara.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the most you can do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, that is much harder to do that than to produce a child.
[SPEAKER_01]: So go and read the sutra on celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then a brahmin, Janasoni, approached the Blessed One and exchanged greetings with Him and said to Him, Does Master Gautama also claim to be one who lives the celibate life?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha replies, if Brahman one could rightly say of anyone, he lives the complete and pure celibate life, unbroken, flawless, unblemished, unstained.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is precisely of me that one might say this.
[SPEAKER_01]: For I live the complete and pure celibate life, unbroken, flawless, unblemished, unstained.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what, Master Gautama, is a breach, flaw, a blemish and a stain of the celibate life?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's here a Brahmin, some ascetic or Brahmin, claiming to be perfectly celibate, does not actually engage in intercourse, sexual intercourse with a woman, but he consents to being rubbed, massaged, bathed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good point, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, some ascetic or brahmana, claiming to be perfectly celibate, does not actually engage in intercourse with women, does not... nor does he consent to being rubbed, massaged, but he jokes with women, plays with them and amuses himself with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he does not joke with women, play with them, and amuse himself with them, but he gazes and stares straight into their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he does not gaze and stare straight into the woman's eyes, but he listens to their voices behind a wall.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, through a rampart, as they laugh, talk, sing, or weep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he does not listen to their voices, voices of women behind a wall, but he recollects laughing, talking, and playing with them in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he does not recollect laughing, talking and playing with them in the past, but he looks at a householder enjoying himself furnished and endowed with five objects of sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he does not look at a householder, enjoying himself furnished and endowed with five objects of sensual pleasure, but he lives the spiritual life, aspiring for rebirth in a certain order of devas, thinking, by this virtuous behavior, observance, and austerity, or spiritual life, I will be a deva, or one in the retinue of the devas.
[SPEAKER_01]: He relishes this desire, and desires it, and finds satisfaction in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This, too, is a breach, a flaw, a blemish and a stain of the celibate life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the perfect celibate life, can't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Perfect, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the reason why I say that is because... Now, people might think, oh, human, I must not do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's actually better to at least be virtuous, even if you are desiring for the sake of rebirth, than to be engaging in sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's that sort of a venerable nānda,
[SPEAKER_00]: was struggling and wanted to disrobe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, why do you want to disrobe?
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, well, there was this servant girl, that was quite pretty, and she told me, when I come back, she'll be waiting for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he said... and then he showed him that the beauty... the Buddha showed him the beauty of the devas.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's 500 nymphs or whatever it was in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he said, well, which is prettier?
[SPEAKER_00]: The nymphs or that servant girl?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, well, the nymphs.
[SPEAKER_00]: The servant girl is like a... Cauterized monkey.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cauterized monkey with the ears burned off.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing in comparison.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, okay, well, I can guarantee you, you're gonna have
[SPEAKER_00]: Those anims, they were anims, if you practice celibacy for the rest of your life, that will be your rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he was like, okay, well, I'll do that then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you got motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, sometime later, the monks heard that and then they were basically looking down upon him and he felt ashamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he actually made the effort properly and became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, it is better, even if you're designing heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is better than than than like committing the kind of animal-like sensuality in this world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not perfect.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the sutta deals with perfect celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not perfect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody says, oh, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do need, like, a person needs to distinguish it's not on the same footing as having sexual intercourse, or allowing women to rub you, or you rubbing them, or listening to them, or talking to them, or depending on their company.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fantasizing about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, you know, if you can't give it all up, well, at least do it, like, do it, like, the last way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about heaven and practice rebirth for that... practice restraint for that sake, for better rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not ultimate, but... but better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it sounds like repression, if you read it, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is repression.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's just people, oh, it's repression.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what?
[SPEAKER_00]: You are in a position to repress.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, like giving in, well, it's... it's... it's... what's the opposite of repression?
[SPEAKER_01]: Opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, given in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indulgent.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess indulgent, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is just repressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you're fighting against saṃsara.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha said you're going against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's exactly what repression is.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing wrong with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, if you go mad and lose it while you were too weak, the grain, you were trying to resist it and it just swept you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tough luck.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you make yourself stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one thing for sure, you'll never become stronger if you practice no repression, no restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And fear of repression is really just fear of going against sensuality, fear of saying no to yourself, no to your own mind, because if you say no, it might rebel and basically drive you mad, which kind of reveals contradiction, which means that mind is not yours, yet you regard it very much as yours, yet you're afraid to say no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But being mine means you're in full control of it, supposedly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you can't say no to yourself, it means you're not in full control of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, that's not your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you should really be afraid when you're giving in to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a scary man knocking on your door.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're afraid to leave the door closed, because he might break it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so you open the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you let him in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's absolutely a non-resistant thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because who knows?
[SPEAKER_00]: He might not be able to break the door if you don't turn it a bit stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you learn how to fortify it before he breaks it.
[SPEAKER_00]: One thing for sure, if you let him in, then you're at his mercy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or maybe he'll take me the good way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe he'll take... maybe he won't harm me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sooner or later, he will harm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha said, that the assassins, the sixth, the sixth is like the assassin, the mind, the dearest, like a dearest friend, that you trust with your life and then he kills you in your sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like the nature of a person's relationship with their own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never question a mind, your own mind, as your own enemy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see it as a dangerous assassin.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just trying to get your sort of your friendship, your trust, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of that sutta, the Buddha still says, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I did not see even one of these seven bonds of sexuality that had not been abandoned, then I claim to have awakened to the unsurpassed perfect enlightenment in this world.
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowledge and vision arose in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unshakable is my liberation of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is my last birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now there is no more renewed existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you saw all that, it was perfectly settled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it was perfectly settled.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind was completely withdrawn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, there's trying to perfect those points.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, not even looking in a woman's eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a time that the Buddha said, if you duke...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have to look... You have to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, all of that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you know, the Buddha was was talking about... and queens and whatever else would come to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to understand that this is all... all these acts are not to be done if they are rooted in sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, don't just deny everything and cover your eyes and run away if there is just a woman on the other side of the road.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just a bit neurotic, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, in the beginning, sure, do it if you can't differentiate, but don't hold that to be the perfect behavior, because one way or the other, you're running away from it, which means it's bothering you, which means you're not free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all this refers to when you're doing it for the sake of, basically, a sexual desire, that then doesn't go... doesn't go to the point of social intercourse, but then you let him touch you, for the sexual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, maybe you don't let him... let him touch you, but then you... you could talk to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You chat him up, just for the enjoyment of sexual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you might not be talking to them, then you're listening to them, looking at them, listening to them, fantasizing about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that's not rooted anymore in any... you obviously wouldn't be fantasizing about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you were to talk to them, for whatever reason, it wouldn't be rooted in that... that, like, a sexuality, in the desire for sex.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just wouldn't be rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might seem a bit rude to people as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sometimes it might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it must.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, again, you recognize, okay, so I'm not supposed to, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Be neurotic about it, but it's better to start a bit neurotic, and then even out, than to start a bit loose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if during your neurotic phase you might be rude, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take, take, you know, own the responsibility for it, but recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, this is just a side effect of the current behavior I'm engaging in, which is like extra slightly neurotic restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's rude, but it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can live with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Better to be rude with the prospect of enlightenment, than polite and ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not justifying rude behavior, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just saying, if you recognize... Yeah, some people are just rude, because they're careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, not to encourage it as well in others, because you can also... it might not be coming from you, but you see the mind of the other is infected by lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that was the point of the... although, like, Aniruddha was an Arahant, he wouldn't have... he couldn't have engaged in any sexual activity with that woman, but Buddha said, but if any other was not an Arahant, was in that circumstances, he most definitely would have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you prevent the circumstance.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: You must not neglect, you must not ignore the fact that it's all for the purpose of developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no end, then, to trying to up... to trying to kind of say no to circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just become... it becomes ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people justify it all because it's the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're doing it out of, as we spoke before, you know, there is the obvious restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you're just going out of this, this, this, like, insane, ridiculous, random measures, like what giants used to do, and just
[SPEAKER_00]: Clearly, just you can see how it evolved, irrationally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way they would go to alms rounds, and then, obviously, get food, but then, it just felt too indulgent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you take food only, I don't know, after every third house.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't take food on the... from... on the person on the right side of the crossroads.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't take food from a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't take food from a pregnant woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't take food from a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't take food... Then, you take food every... Then, you don
[SPEAKER_00]: That's often the attitude people might have.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might not take it in that regard, but when it comes to, like, telling no and just fear, and then just no to this, no to this, no to this, then it becomes ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's saying...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely irrational, and by giving in, by encouraging that irrational behavior, you forget that your responsibility... well, that your responsibility is to develop wisdom on the basis of restraint you're practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you forget about that dimension, and all you end up doing is investing more effort in just restraining your restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you're already restrained, there is no need to push it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leave it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Leave it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just go back and keep tightening already things that are already tight enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that restraint, obviously, was not... not fan... just not fantasizing about sexual behavior, will reveal that craving to go in that direction, that need for that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will just be revealed.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're looking for it, it will show you straight away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if all you're looking for is the next step for your restraint, after this completely restrained, every aspect, yet you then just keep, okay, restrain further and further, you'll never stop and look back and see what the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The craving, the desire, the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which is always
[SPEAKER_01]: And just to read that sūtra we spoke about in the beginning, called Union and Disengagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I will teach you a dhamma exposition on union and disengagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is that dhamma exposition on union and disengagement?
[SPEAKER_01]: A woman attends internally to her feminine faculty, her feminine comportment, her feminine appearance, her feminine aspect, her feminine desire, her feminine voice, her feminine ornaments.
[SPEAKER_01]: She becomes excited by these and takes delight in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: His masculine comportment, his masculine appearance, his masculine aspect, his masculine desire, his masculine voice, his masculine ornaments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Excited by them, taking delight in them, she desires union externally and she also desires the pleasure and joy that arise on account of such union.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beings who are delighted with their femininity enter upon union with men.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is in this way that a woman does not transcend her femininity and likewise with a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the opposite, where she doesn't attend to her femininity, then there's disengagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's not entertaining the basis for all those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no delight in the feminine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of blaming men, or men blame women, just uproot the delight in your own manliness, or in your own femininity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uproot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was that sutta where the monk couldn't free himself from... oh, no, I think that was in the rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I think it was the sutta, actually, when he couldn't free himself from sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he kind of started going mad and he cut his sexual organ off.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it was foolish, you did.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, instead of cutting one thing, he cut a wrong thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cutting ignorance, instead of that, he cut, he cut his penis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, cutting his masculinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's... because that's not your masculinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance, in regard to the masculine form, is masculinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can have all the masculine form you want, if you're not ignorant in regard to it, if you're not delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you see it as impermanent, if you see it as not personal, not dear to you, not yours, not internally held...
[SPEAKER_00]: Same for a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever you're born, you'll always be that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody wants you to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't yours to begin with, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you were to truly own that form, it wouldn't age.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't get sick, it wouldn't die.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has its own course, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that course is the course of impermanence.